Wonder by RJ palaso breakfast CAN YOU PICK me up from school today?” I said the next morning,
smearing some cream cheese on my bagel.
Mom was making August’s lunch (American cheese on whole wheat bread, soft enough
for Augie to eat) while August set eating oatmeal at the table. Dad was getting
ready to go to work. Now that I was in high school, the new school routine was
going to be that Dad and I would take the subway together in the morning, which
meant his having to leave 15 minutes earlier than usual, then I’d get off at
my stop and he’d keep going. And Mom was
going to pick me up after school in the car. “I was going to call Miranda’s mother
to see if she could drive you home again,” Mom answered. “No, Mom!” I said quickly. “You
pick me up. Or I’ll just take the
subway.” “You know I don’t want you to take the subway by yourself yet,” she answered.
“Mom, I’m 15 Everybody my age takes the subway by themselves!” “She can take the subway home,”
said Dad from the other room, adjusting his tie as he stepped into the kitchen.
“Why can’t Miranda’s mother just pick her up again?” Mom argued with him. “She’s old
enough to take the subway by herself,” Dad insisted. Mom looked at both of us. “Is
something going on?” She didn’t address her question to
either one of us in particular. “You would know if you had come back to check on me,”
I said spitefully, “like you said you would.” “Oh God, Via,” said Mom, remembering
now how she had completely ditched me last night. She put down the knife she
was using to cut Auggie’s grapes in half (still a choking hazard for him because
of the size of his pallette I am so sorry. I fell asleep in Auggie’s room. By
the time I woke up up “I know, I know.” I nodded indifferently. Mom came over, put
her hands on my cheeks, and lifted my face to look at
her. “I’m really, really sorry,” she whispered. I could tell she was. “It’s okay!”
I said. “Via “Mom, it’s fine.” This time I meant it. She looks so genuinely sorry I
just wanted to let her off the hook. She kissed and hugged me, then returned into the
grapes. “So, is something going on with Miranda?” she asked. “Just that she’s acting like a
complete jerk,” I said. “Miranda’s not a jerk!” Auggie quickly chimed in. “She can be!”
I yelled. “Believe me.” “Okay then, I’ll pick you up, no problem,”
Mom said decisively, sweeping the half grapes into a snack bag with the side of
her knife. “That was the plan all along anyway.
I’ll pick Auggie up from school in the
car and then we’ll pick you up. We’ll probably get there about a quarter to
four.” “No!” I said firmly, before she’d even finished Isabelle she can take the
subway!” said Dad impatiently. “She’s a big girl now. She’s reading War in Peace for
crying out loud.” “What does War in Peace have to do with anything?” answered Mom, clearly
annoyed. “It means you don’t have to pick
her up in a car like she’s a little girl,”
he said sternly. “Via, are you ready? Get
your bag and let’s go.” “I’m ready,” I said,
pulling on my backpack. “Bye, Mom! Bye Augie I kissed them both quickly and headed
toward the door. “Do you even have a metro card Mom said after me. “Of course she has
a metro card answered Dad, fully exasperated G mama Stop worrying so much!
Bye,” he said, kissing her on the cheek. “Bye, big boy,” he said to August, kissing him on
the top of his head. “I’m proud of you.
Have a good day.” “Bye, Daddy! You to Dad and I jogged down the stoop stairs and
headed down the block. “Call me after school before you get on the subway!” Mom
yelled at me from the window. I didn’t even turn around but waved my hand at
her so she’d know I heard her. Dad did turn around, walking backward for a few
steps. War in Peace Isabelle he called out, smiling as he pointed at me. War and Peace genetics
101 BOTH SIDES OF Dad’s family were Jews from Russia and Poland Papa's
grandparents fled the pilgrims and ended up in NYC at the turn of the century.
Tata’s parents fled the Nazis and ended up in Argentina in the 40s Papa and Tata
met at a dance on the Lower East Side while she was in town visiting a cousin.
They got married, moved to Bayside, and had Dad and Uncle Ben. Mom’s side of the
family is from Brazil. Except for her mother, my beautiful Grands and her dad
austa who died before I was born, the rest of Mom’s family— —all her glamorous
aunts, uncles, and cousins— —still live in Alto leblan a ritzy suburb south of Rio
gr and austo moved to Boston in the early 60s and had Mom and Aunt Kate who
was married to Uncle Porter. Mom and Dad met at Brown University and have been
together ever since Isabelle and Nate: like two peas in a PO They moved to New
York right after college, had me a few years later, then moved to a brick
townhouse in North River Heights, the hippie stroller capital of upper upper
Manhattan, when I was about a year old.
Not one person in the exotic mix of my family Jean pool has ever shown any
obvious signs of having what August has.
I’ve poured over grainy sepia pictures of long dead relatives and babushkas
black and white snapshots of distant cousins in crisp white linen suits,
soldiers in uniform, ladies with beehive haird Polaroids of bellbottom teenagers
and long-haired hippies, and not once have I been able to detect even the
slightest trace of August’s face and their faces. Not a one. But after August
was born, my parents underwent genetic counseling. They were told that August
had what seem to be a “previously unknown type of mandibulofacial DSis caused by
an autosomal recessive mutation in the tcf1 gene, which is located on chromosome
5, complicated by a hemifacial microsomia characteristic of OAV
spectrum.” Sometimes these mutations occur during pregnancy. Sometimes they’re
inherited from one parent carrying the dominant gene. Sometimes they’re caused
by the interaction of many genes possi in combination with environmental
factors. This is called multifactoral inheritance. In August’s case doctors
were able to identify one of the “single nucleotide dele mutations” that made war
on his face. The weird thing is that you’d never know it from looking at them:
both my parents carry that mutant gene. And I carry it,
too the punet square IF I HAVE children, there’s a one and two chance chance that
I will pass on the defective gene to them. That doesn’t mean they’ll look like
August, but they’ll carry the Jean that got double do in August and help make
him the way he is. If I marry someone who
has the same defect of gene, there’s a one and two chance that our kids will
carry the gene and look totally normal, a one in four chance that our kids will
not carry the gene at all, and a one in four chance that our kids will look like
August. If August has children with someone who doesn’t have a trace of the
gene, there’s a 100% probability that their kids will inherit the gene, but a
0% chance that their kids will have a double dose of it, like August. Which
means they’ll carry the gene no matter what, but they could look totally normal.
If he marries someone who has the gene, their kids will have the same odds as my
kids. This only explains the part of August that’s explainable. There’s that
other part of his genetic makeup that’s not inherited but just incredibly bad
luck. Countless doctors have drawn little Tic Tac Toe grids for my parents over
the years to try to explain the genetic lottery to them. Geneticists use these
Punit squares to determine inheritance, recessive and dominant genes,
probabilities and chance. But for all they know, there’s more they don’t know.
They can try to forecast the odds, but they can’t guarantee them. They use terms like “germline
mosaicism,” “chromosome rearrangement,” or “delayed mutation” to explain why their
science is not an exact science actually like how doctors talk. I like the sound
of science. I like how words you don’t understand explain things you can’t
understand. There are countless people under words like “germline
mosaicism,” “chromosome rear Arrangement or “delayed mutation.” Countless babies who’ll
never be born, like mine out with the old MIRANDA AND ELLA
blasted off. They attached themselves to a new crowd destined for high school
glory. After a week of painful lunches where all they would do was talk about
people that didn’t interest me, I decided to make a clean break for it. They asked
no questions. I told no lies. We just went our separate ways. I didn’t even mind
after a while. I stopped going to lunch for about a week, though, to make the
transition easier, to avoid the fake Oh, shoot, there’s no room for you at the table,
Olivia! It was easier just to go to the library and read. I finished War and
Peace in October. It was amazing. People think it’s such a hard
read, but it’s really just a soap operate with lots of characters, people falling
in love, fighting for love, dying for love.
I want to be in love like that someday. I want my husband to love me the way
Prince Andre loved Natasha. I ended up hanging out with a
girl named Elanor who' I’d known from my days at PS22, though we' gone to different middle
schools Elanor had always been a really smart girl— —a little bit of a crybaby
back then, but nice I never realized how funny she was (not laugh out loud Daddy
funny but full of great quips), and she never knew how light-hearted I could be.
Eleanor, I guess, had always been under the impression that I was very serious.
And, as it turns out she never liked Miranda and Ella. She thought they were
stuck up I gained entry through Eleanor to the smart kids table at lunch. It was
a larger group than I’d been accustomed to hanging out with, and a more diverse
crowd. It included Eleanor’s boyfriend, Kevin, who would definitely become class
president someday; a few techy guys; girls like Eleanor who were members of the
yearbook committee and the debate club; and a quiet guy named Justin who had
small round glasses and played the violin, and who I had an instant crush on.
When I’d see Miranda and Ella, who were now hanging out with the super popular
set, we’d say “Hey, what’s up up,” and move on. Occasionally Miranda would ask me how
August was doing, and then say “Tell him I say hello.” This I never did, not despite
Miranda, but because August was in his own world these days. There were times, at
home, that we never crossed paths October 31st gr HAD DIED the night before
Halloween. Since then, even though it’s been four years, this has always been a
sad time of year for me. For Mom, too, though she doesn’t always say it. Instead,
she immerses herself in getting August’s costume ready, since we all know
Halloween is his favorite time of year.
This year was no different. August really wanted to be a Star Wars character named
Boba Fett, so Mom looked for a Boba Fett costume in August’s size, which, strangely
enough, was out of stock everywhere. She went to every online store, found a few
on eBay that were going for an outrageous amount, and finally ended up
buying a d Jango fet costume that she then converted into a Boba Fett costume
by painting it green. I would say, in all, she must have spent two weeks working on
that stupid costume. And no, I won’t mention the fact that Mom has never made
any of my costumes, because it really has no bearing ing on anything at all. The
morning of Halloween I woke up thinking about Grand's which made me really sad
and weepy. Dad kept telling me to hurry up and get dressed, which just stressed
me out even more, and suddenly I started crying. I just wanted to stay home. So Dad
took August to school that morning and Mom said I could stay home, and the two
of us cried together for a while. One thing I knew for sure: however much I missed GR
Mom must have missed her more. All those times August was clinging to life after
a surgery, all those rush trips to the ER Grant had always been there for Mom. It
felt good to cry with Mom. For both of us.
At some point, Mom had the idea of our watching The Ghost and Mrs Mir together,
which was one of our all-time favorite black and white movies. I agree that that
was a great idea. I think I probably would have used this weeping session as
an opportunity to tell Mom everything that was going on at school with Miranda
and Ella, but just as we were sitting down in front of the DVD player, the
phone rang. It was the nurse from August’s school calling to tell Mom that
August had a stomach a and should be picked up. So much for the old movies and
the mother daughter bonding. Mom picked August up, and the
moment he came home, he went straight to the bathroom and threw up. Then he went
to his bed and pulled the covers over his head. Mom took his temperature,
brought him some hot tea, and assumed the “August’s mom roll again. “Via’s mom,” who
had come out for a little while, was put away. I understood, though: August was in
bad shape. Neither one of us asked him why he had worn his Bleeding screen
costume to school instead of the Boba Fett costume Mom had made for him. If it
annoyed Mom to see the costume she had worked on for 2 weeks tossed on the
floor, unused, she didn’t show it trick or treat AUGUST SAID HE wasn’t
feeling well enough to go trick-or-treating later in the afternoon,
which was sad for him because I know how much he loved to trick-or treat
especially after it got dark outside.
Even though I was well beyond the trick-or-treating stage myself, I usually
threw on some mask or other to accompany him up and down the blocks, watching him
knocking on people’s doors, giddy with excitement. I knew it was the one night a
year he could truly be like every other kid. No one knew he was different under
the mask. To August, that must have felt absolutely amazing. At 7:00 that night, I knocked on
his door. “Hey,” I said. “Hey,” he said back. He wasn’t using his PlayStation or reading
a comic book. He was just lying in his bed looking at the ceiling da e as
always, was next to him on the bed, her head draped over his legs. The Bleeding
Scream costume was crumpled up on the floor next to the Boba Fett costume.
“How’s your stomach?” I said, sitting next to him on the bed. “I’m still
nauseous you're sure you’re not up for the Halloween Parade?”
“Positive.” This surprised me. Usually August was such a trooper about his
medical issues, whether it was skateboarding if few days after a
surgery or sipping food through a straw when his mouth was practically bolted
shut. This was a kid who’s gotten more shots, taken more medicines, put up with
more procedures by the age of 10 than most people would have put up with in 10
lifetimes, and he was sidelined from a little nausea? “You want to tell me what’s up?” I
said, sounding a bit like Mom. “No.” “Is it school?” “Yes.” “Teachers?
Schoolwork?
Friends?” He didn’t answer. “Did someone say something?” I
asked. “People always say something,” he answered bitterly. I could tell he was close to
crying. “Tell me what happened,” I said. And he told me what happened. He had
overheard some very mean things some boys were saying about him. He didn’t
care about what the other boys boys had said, he expected that, but he was hurt
that one of the boys was his “best friend” Jack Will. I remembered his mentioning
Jack a couple of times over the past few months. I remembered Mom and Dad saying
he seemed like a really nice kid, saying they were glad August had already made a friend like
that. “Sometimes kids are stupid,” I said softly, holding his hand. “I’m sure he
didn’t mean it.” “Then why would he say it?
He’s been pretending to be my friend all along. Tushman probably bribed him with a
good grade or something. I bet you he was like, hey, Jack, if you make friends with
the freak, you don’t have to take any tests this year.” “You know that’s not true.
And don’t call yourself a freak.” “Whatever. I wish I’d never gone to
school in the first place.” “But I thought you were liking
it.” “I hate it!” He was angry all of a sudden, punching his pillow. “I hate it! I
hate it! I hate it!” He was shrieking at the top of his lungs. I didn’t say
anything. I didn’t know what to say. He
was hurt. He was mad. I let him have a few more minutes of his fury. Daisy started
licking the tears off his face. “Come on, Auggie,” I said, patting his back gently.
“Why don’t you put on your D Jango Fett
costume and—” “It’s a Boba Fett costume! Why do every everyone mix that up?” “Boba Fett
costume,” I said, trying to stay calm. I put my arm around his shoulders. “Let’s just
go to the parade, okay?” “If I go to the parade, Mom will think I’m feeling better
and make me go to school tomorrow.” “Mom would never make you go to school,” I
answered. “Come on, Auggie. Let’s just go.
It’ll be fun, I promise. And I’ll let you
have all my candy.” He didn’t argue. He got out of bed and slowly started pulling on
his Boba fet costume. I helped him adjust the straps and tighten the belt, and by
the time he put his helmet on, I could tell he was feeling
better time to think AUGUST PLAYED UP the stomach ache the next day so he
wouldn’t have to go to school. I admit I felt a little bad for Mom, who was
generally concerned that he had a stomach bug, but I had promised August I
wouldn’t tell her about the incident at school. By Sunday, he was still determined
not to to go back to school. “What are you planning on telling Mom and Dad?” I asked
him when he told me this. “They said I could quit whenever I wanted to.” He said
this while he was still focused on a comic book he was reading. “But you’ve
never been the kind of kid who quits things,” I said truthfully. “That’s not like
you.” “I’m quitting.” “You’re going to have to tell Mom and Dad why,” I pointed out,
pulling the comic book out of his hand
so he’d have to look at me while we were talking. “Then Mom will call the school
and everyone will know about it.” “Will Jack get in
trouble?” “I would think so.” “Good.” I have to admit, August was surprising me more and
more. He pulled another comic book off his shelf and started leaping through it
Augie I said. “Are you really going to let a couple of stupid kids keep you from
going back to school? I know you’ve been enjoying it. Don’t give them that power
over you. Don’t give them the satisfaction.” “They have no idea I even
heard them,” he explained. “No, I know, but
“Via, it’s okay. I know what I’m doing. I’ve
made up my mind.” “But this is crazy, Auggie!” I said emphatically, pulling the new
comic book away from him, too. “You have to go back to school. Everyone hates school
sometimes. I hate school sometimes S I hate my friends sometimes. That’s just
life, Auggie. You want to be treated normally, right? This is normal! We all
have to go to school sometimes despite the fact that we have bad days, okay?” “Do
people go out of their way to avoid touching you, Via?” he answered, which left
me momentarily without an answer. “Yeah, right. That’s what I thought. So don’t
compare your bad days at school to mine, okay?” “Okay, that’s fair,” I said. “But it’s
not a contest about whose days suck the most, Auggie. The point is we all have to
put up with the bad days. Now, unless you want to be treated like a baby the rest
of your life, or like a kid with special
needs, you just have to suck it up and go.”
He didn’t say anything, but I think that last bit was getting to him. “You don’t
have to say a word to those kids,” I continued. “August, actually, it’s so cool
that you know what they said, but they don’t know you know what they said, you
know?” “What the heck?” “You know what I mean.
You don’t have to talk to them ever again, if you don’t want. And they’ll
never know why. See? Or you can pretend to be friends with them, but deep down
inside you know you’re not.” “Is that how you are with Miranda?” he asked. “No,” I
answered quickly, defensively. “I I never faked my feelings with
Miranda.” “So why are you saying I should?” “I’m not! I’m just saying you shouldn’t
let those little jerks get to you, that’s all.” “Like Miranda got to you.” “Why do you
keep bringing Miranda up?” I yelled impatiently. “I’m trying to talk to you
about your friends. Please keep mine out of it.” “You’re not even friends with her
anymore.” “What does that have to do with what we’re talking about?” The way August
was looking at me reminded me of a doll’s face. He was just staring at me
blankly with his half closed doll eyes.
“She called the other day,” he said finally.
“What?” I was stunned. “And you didn’t tell me?” “She wasn’t calling you,” he answered,
pulling both comic books out of my hands.
“She was calling me. Just to say hi. To see
how I was doing. She didn’t even know I
was going to a real school now. I can’t believe you hadn’t even told her. She
said that two of you don’t hang out as much anymore, but she wanted me to know
she’d always love me like a big sister double stunned Stung.
Flabbergasted. No words formed in my mouth. “Why didn’t you tell me?” I said,
finally. “I don’t know.” He shrugged, opening the first comic book
again. “Well, I’m telling Mom and Dad about Jack Will if you stop going to school,” I
answered. “Tushman will probably call you into school and make Jack and those
other kids apologize to you in front of everyone, and everyone will treat you
like a kid who should be going to a school for kids with special needs. Is
that what you want? Because that’s what’s going to happen. Otherwise, just go back
to school and act like nothing happened.
Or if you want to confront Jack about it, fine. But either way, if you—” “Fine. Fine.
Fine,” he interrupted. “What?” “Fine! I’ll go!” he yelled, not not loudly. “Just stop talking
about it already. Can I please read my book now?” “Fine!” I answered. Turning to
leave his room, I thought of something.
“Did Miranda say anything else about me?” He looked up from the comic book and
looked right in my eyes. “She said to tell you she misses you.
Quote unquote.” I nodded. “Thanks,” I said casually, too embarrassed to let him see
how happy that made me feel thanks for listening please like
And subscribe become a channel member we'll see you in another story
[Music]